Finding Aid for Michigan Historical Records Survey records, 1936-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Survey of Municipal Records
  - Detroit
    - Inventory of Government Department Holdings
      - Common Council (Reel 35)
      - Common Pleas Court (Reel 35)
      - Controller's Office (Reel 35)
      - Controller's Office (cont.) (Reel 36)
      - Corporation Counsel (Reel 36)
      - Board of Education (Reel 36)
      - Election Commission (Reel 36)
      - Board of Estimates (Reel 36)
      - Fire Commission and Department (Reel 36)
      - Board of Health (Reel 36)
      - Public Library (Reel 36)
      - Public Lighting Commission (Reel 36)
      - Public Lighting Commission (cont.) (Reel 37)
      - Mayor's Office (Reel 37)
      - Department of Parks and Boulevards (Reel 37)
      - City Planning Commission (Reel 37)
      - Police Department (Reel 37)
      - Probate Court (including County Agent and Juvenile Court) (Reel 37)
      - Department of Purchases and Supplies (Reel 37)
      - Recorder's Court (Reel 37)
      - Recorder's Court-Psychopathic Clinic (Reel 37)
      - Sinking Fund Commission (Reel 37)
      - Department of Street Railways (Reel 37)
      - Department of Street Railways (cont.) (Reel 38)
      - City Treasurer (Reel 38)
      - Department of Water Supply (Reel 38)
      - Department of Water Supply (cont.) (Reel 39)
      - Department of Public Welfare (Reel 39)
      - Department of Public Works (Reel 39)
      - Department of Public Works (cont.) (Reel 40)
      - City Engineer's Office (Reel 40)
      - City Engineer's Office (cont.) (Reel 41)
      - Sewage Treatment Plant (Reel 41)
  - Escanaba
    - Correspondence (Reel 41)
    - Historical Material (Reel 41)
    - Historical Material (cont.) (Reel 42)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 42)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 42)
  - Grand Rapids
    - Historical Material (Reel 42)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 42)
  - Hamtramck
    - Correspondence (Reel 42)
    - Historical Material (Reel 42)
    - Service Organizations (Reel 42)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 43)
  - Jackson
    - Historical Material (Reel 43)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
  - Kalamazoo
    - Historical Material (Reel 43)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
  - Marquette
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 43)
  - Menominee
    - Historical Material (Reel 43)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
  - Muskegon
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
  - Port Huron
    - Historical Material (Reel 43)
    - Historical Material-Government Organization (Reel 43)
    - Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (Reel 43)
- Survey of Federal Records
  The Survey of Federal Records series is a tiny part of the H.R.S. collection, consisting of only two categories of unpublished records (and a couple of inches of linear shelf space): Field Agencies of the Federal Government and Directory of Buildings and Rooms Containing Federal Archives. The former gives brief profiles of agencies and their records, but does not include inventories. Several inventories had been published and are in the Bentley Library's printed collection. Volumes on the Federal Emergency Relief Administration, the Works Progress Administration, and the Post Office had been prepared for publication; these have been bound and treated as separate entities in the printed collection. The Directory of Buildings and Rooms Containing Federal Archives was also ready for publication, but is now so outdated that it would no longer be accurate and so has been microfilmed but not bound.
  - Field Agencies of the Federal Government (Reel 44)
  - Directory of Buildings and Rooms containing Federal Archives (Reel 44)
- Survey of State Records
  The Survey of State Records series is also very small (less than a linear foot), containing the histories and/or inventories of only six agencies: Administrative Board, Auditor General, Conservation Department, State Board of Health, Judicial Circuits, and Liquor Control Commission. As with historical information in the county and municipal files, notes from sources readily available or better consulted elsewhere have been discarded. Only the most advanced form of an essay has been retained and the original order of the inventory forms has been preserved.
  - Administrative Board (history and inventory) (Reel 44)
  - Auditor General (history) (Reel 44)
  - Conservation Department (inventory) (Reel 44)
  - State Board of Health (inventory) (Reel 44)
  - Judicial Circuits (history) (Reel 44)
  - Liquor Control Commission (history) (Reel 44)
- WPA Project Files
  The WPA Project Files comprise about one and one-half linear feet of material and consist of correspondence, official bulletins, descriptions of projects, instructions to workers, lists of workers, project proposals, work reports, and lists of publications for the following projects (though not all for each): Historical Records Survey, Statewide Museums Project, National Youth Administration (whose workers assisted in both of these projects), Art Program, American Imprints Inventory of Michigan, and Michigan Writers Project. Also included are the files of the Survey of Civilian Organizations in Ann Arbor, which consists of forms filled out on each of the large number of groups that were active then. Much was discarded in the processing of the WPA Project Files: insignificant or routine correspondence, trivial work reports, and the ever-present duplicates. A few items relating to the Historical Records Survey and the Statewide Museums Project have been retained but not microfilmed (see contents list).
  - Official bulletins, memoranda, etc. relating to administration, personnel, projects (Reel 44)
  - Correspondence of the State Advisory Committee for Community Service Programs 1941-1942 (Reel 45)
  - Correspondence relating to projects 1937-1941
    - Manuscripts Survey (Reel 45)
    - Michigan Imprints Survey (Reel 45)
    - Church Survey (Reel 45)
    - Historical Records Survey (Reel 45)
  - Historical Records Survey
    - Descriptions of the project (Reel 45)
    - HRS brochure (Box 46)
      (not microfilmed)
    - Instructions to workers (Reel 45)
    - WPA forms and instructions
      - 10HR: County Buildings (Reel 45)
      - 10HR: Offices or Vaults (Reel 45)
      - 12-13HR: Volumes and Unbound Records (Reel 45)
      - 14HR: Newspapers (Reel 45)
      - 15HR: Maps and Photographs (Reel 45)
      - 16HR: Art Objects (Reel 45)
      - 17HR: Manuscript Collections (Reel 45)
      - 19HR: Individual Manuscripts (Reel 45)
      - 21HR: Manuscript Depositories (Reel 45)
      - 23HR: Vital Statistics Records (Reel 45)
      - 27HR: Institutions (willing to accept deposits) (Reel 45)
      - 28HR: Buildings (Reel 45)
      - 29HR: Rooms or Vaults (Reel 45)
      - 30HR: Institutions (desiring to remove materials) (Reel 45)
    - Outlines for workers to follow and sources of information (Reel 45)
    - Critiques on Guides in progress (Reel 45)
    - Retired inventories of the HRS collection (Reel 45)
  - Statewide Museums Project
    - Descriptions of the project, lists of workers (Reel 45)
    - Correspondence within Michigan 1938-1941 (Reel 45)
    - Correspondence within Michigan 1942 (Reel 46)
    - Correspondence with other states 1939-1941 (Reel 46)
    - Project proposals (Reel 46)
    - Progress reports
      - Quarterly reports of the project 1939-1942 (Reel 46)
      - Monthly reports of the museums and units
        - District 2
          - Kalamazoo 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
          - Battle Creek 1939 (Reel 46)
          - Holland 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
          - Grand Rapids
            - Art Gallery 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
            - Public Museum 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
          - Map Construction 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
        - District 3
          - Lansing
            - Pioneer Museum 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
            - School for the Blind 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
          - East Lansing, Michigan State College
            - Home Economics 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
            - Conservation Institute 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
            - Library Museum 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
            - Agricultural Engineering Dept. 1939 (Reel 46)
            - Geology and Geography 1939 (Reel 46)
          - Port Huron 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
          - Alpena 1939 (Reel 46)
          - Ann Arbor
            - University Museums 1939-1942 (Reel 46)
            - Source Unit 1939 (Reel 46)
        - District 4
          - Detroit
            - Children's Museum 1938-1939 (Reel 46)
            - Detroit Historical Museum 1939 (Reel 46)
            - Detroit Historical Society 1939 (Reel 46)
            - Diorama Construction 1939 (Reel 46)
            - WPA Building (University of Michigan Archaeological Laboratories Project) 1941-1942 (Reel 46)
    - Miscellaneous reports (Reel 46)
    - Brochures and newspaper clippings (Box 46)
    - Photographs
  - National Youth Administration (Reel 46)
  - Art Program: descriptions and letters concerning proposed merger with Museums Project (Reel 46)
  - American Imprints Inventory-Michigan
    - Descriptions of the project (Reel 46)
    - Procedures (Reel 46)
    - Forms returned from libraries (Reel 46)
    - Correspondence 1938-1941 (Reel 47)
  - Michigan Writers Project
    - Descriptions of the project (Reel 47)
    - Instructions to workers (Reel 47)
    - Lists of publications
      - Michigan Writers Project (Reel 47)
      - Federal Writers Project (Reel 47)
    - Correspondence 1940-1942 (Reel 47)
    - Land Acquisition Study (Reel 47)
    - Study of history of logging in Michigan (Reel 47)
    - Workers' applications and writing samples (Reel 47)
  - Survey of Civilian Organizations in Ann Arbor (Reel 47)
- Manuscript Survey
  The Manuscripts Survey series consists is organized into two subseries: Survey of Manuscript Depositories in Michigan and Survey of Private Collections.
  - Survey of Manuscript Depositories in Michigan
    The Survey of Manuscripts Depositories in Michigan, comprising less than half of a linear foot, is arranged alphabetically by city and consists of descriptions of the depositories, correspondence, and inventories. This unpublished group of records supplements the published Guide to Manuscript Depositories in the United States - Michigan, issued by the H.R.S. in 1940. Material discarded from this subseries included duplicates, routine correspondence, trivial reports, and illegible notes.
    - Adrian
      - Adrian College Library (Reel 47)
      - Adrian Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Albion
      - Alumni Hall, Albion College (Reel 47)
      - Albion College Library (Reel 47)
      - Albion Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Allegan
      - Allegan Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Ann Arbor
      - Michigan Historical Collections, University of Michigan (Reel 47)
    - Bay City
      - Bay County Historical Association Museum (Reel 47)
    - Benton Harbor
      - Benton Harbor Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Detroit
      - Burton Historical Collection, Detroit Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Flint
      - Flint Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Flushing
      - Flushing Township Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Grand Haven
      - Grand Haven Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Grand Rapids
      - Ryerson Library (Reel 47)
      - Grand Rapids Public Museum (Reel 47)
    - Grayling
      - Hartwick Pines Memorial Park (Reel 47)
    - Hartland
      - Cromaine Hall, Waldenwoods (Reel 47)
      - Cromaine Library (Reel 47)
      - Hartland Music Hall (Reel 47)
    - Hastings
      - Barry County Museum, Charlton Park (Reel 47)
    - Hillsdale
      - Mitchell Public Library (Reel 47)
    - Holland
      - Museum of the Netherlands (Reel 47)
      - Graves Library, Hope College (Reel 47)
    - Houghton
      - Keweenaw Historical Society (Reel 47)
    - Hudson
      - Hudson Library (Reel 47)
    - Ithaca
      - Thompson Home Library (Reel 47)
    - Jackson
      - Jackson City Library (Reel 47)
    - Kalamazoo
      - Ladies' Library Association (Reel 47)
      - Minnie Mandelle Library, Kalamazoo College (Reel 48)
      - Kalamazoo Public Library (Reel 48)
      - Kalamazoo Public Library Museum (Reel 48)
    - Lansing
      - Michigan Historical Commission (Reel 48)
      - Michigan State Library (Reel 48)
      - Secretary of State, Compiling Division (Reel 48)
    - Mackinac Island
      - Astor House Association (Reel 48)
    - Marquette
      - Marquette County Historical Society (Reel 48)
    - Marshall
      - Marshall Historical Society (Reel 48)
    - Mason
      - Historical Museum (Reel 48)
    - Menominee
      - Menominee High School (Reel 48)
    - Nazareth
      - Nazareth College Library (Reel 48)
    - Niles
      - Fort St. Joseph Historical Museum (Reel 48)
    - Pontiac
      - Oakland County Pioneer and Historical Society (Reel 48)
    - Port Huron
      - Port Huron Public Library (Reel 48)
    - Saginaw
      - Hoyt Public Library (Reel 48)
    - Sault Ste. Marie
      - Carnegie Public Library (Reel 48)
    - South Haven
      - Zachariah Chandler Post, G.A.R. (Reel 48)
      - Three Oaks (Reel 48)
      - Chamberlain Memorial Museum (Reel 48)
    - Three Rivers
      - Three Rivers Public Library (Reel 48)
    - Traverse City
      - Traverse City Museum (Reel 48)
  - Survey of Private Collections
    The Survey of Private Collections subseries, comprising two linear feet of material, consists of inventories (and sometimes transcripts and/or translations) of manuscripts, genealogies, newspapers, printed material, scrapbooks and newspaper clippings, deeds, birth records, and army discharges - a genealogical gold mine. These records had been arranged roughly by type and then by county within that classification, but with a lot of overlapping. During processing, this arrangement scheme was changed so that all types of records are now grouped together by county.
    - Alcona County (Reel 48)
    - Allegan County (Reel 48)
    - Alpena County (Reel 48)
    - Baraga County (Reel 48)
    - Barry County (Reel 48)
    - Bay County (Reel 48)
    - Berrien County (Reel 48)
    - Branch County (Reel 49)
    - Calhoun County (Reel 49)
    - Cass County (Reel 49)
    - Charlevoix County (Reel 50)
    - Chippewa County (Reel 50)
    - Crawford County (Reel 50)
    - Delta County (Reel 50)
    - Dickinson County (Reel 50)
    - Eaton County (Reel 50)
    - Emmet County (Reel 50)
    - Genesee County (Reel 50)
    - Grand Traverse County (Reel 50)
    - Gratiot County (Reel 50)
    - Hillsdale County (Reel 50)
    - Huron County (Reel 50)
    - Ingham County (Reel 50)
    - Iosco County (Reel 50)
    - Iron County (Reel 50)
    - Isabella County (Reel 50)
    - Jackson County (Reel 50)
    - Kalamazoo County (Reel 50)
    - Kalamazoo County (cont.) (Reel 51)
    - Kent County (Reel 51)
    - Keweenaw County (Reel 51)
    - Lapeer County (Reel 51)
    - Leelanau County (Reel 51)
    - Lenawee County (Reel 51)
    - Livingston County (Reel 51)
    - Mackinac County (Reel 51)
    - Macomb County (Reel 51)
    - Manistee County (Reel 51)
    - Marquette County (Reel 51)
    - Menominee County (Reel 51)
    - Midland County (Reel 51)
    - Missaukee County (Reel 51)
    - Monroe County (Reel 51)
    - Oakland County (Reel 51)
    - Ottawa County (Reel 51)
    - Saginaw County (Reel 51)
    - St. Clair County (Reel 51)
    - St. Joseph County (Reel 51)
    - Shiawassee County (Reel 51)
    - Tuscola County (Reel 51)
    - Van Buren County (Reel 51)
    - Washtenaw County (Reel 51)
- Inventory of Negro manuscript
  The Inventory of Negro Manuscripts (comprising less than a linear foot of material) also contains a great deal of genealogical information. There are biographies (see the contents list for itemization) and inventories of private collections (sometimes with transcripts), including manuscripts, books, photographs, newspaper articles, and talks given. The H.R.S. workers sometimes filed these materials according to who produced them and sometimes according to who owned them at the time of the inventory, a system that might lead to some confusion but which has been retained.
  The biographies and the inventories of collections make up the bulk of this record subgroup, but in addition there are descriptions of the survey project; a bibliography; an essay entitled "History of the Negro in Michigan", attributed to Robert Hayden and similar to the one bound into the unpublished volume of the same name mentioned earlier; and transcripts of papers, complementing those published in the calendar section of that book. Discarded were duplicates and early drafts of essays, drafts of the published Calendar of the John C. Dancy Correspondence, 1898-1910 and the unpublished calendar, inventory forms for items listed in the calendar, and library notes taken from standard biographical sources. The Inventory of Negro Manuscripts has been preserved in manuscript form as well as on microfilm. (see Box 45 for original documents)
  - Description of the Project (Reel 52)
  - Bibliography (Reel 52)
  - "History of the Negro in Michigan" (Reel 52)
    (essay similar to that which was published in the Historical Records Survey's book of that name; both attributed to Robert Hayden)
  - Transcripts of Papers (Reel 52)
    (not used in the published calendar, but complementing those that were)
  - Biographies
    - Dancy, John C. (Reel 52)
    - Ferguson, William (Reel 52)
    - Finney, Seymour (Reel 52)
    - Harvard, Claude (Reel 52)
    - Lambert, William (Reel 52)
    - Loomis, Lloyd (Reel 52)
    - McCoy, Elijah (Reel 52)
    - Morris, Henry (Reel 52)
    - Sheley, Alanson (Reel 52)
    - Shewcraft, Richard Turner (Reel 52)
    - Straker, D. Augustus (Reel 52)
    - Ward, Willis (Reel 52)
    - Washington, Booker T. (Reel 52)
    - Willis, Robert (Reel 52)
    - Willoughby, Benjamin (Reel 52)
    - Wilson, Alfred W. (Reel 52)
    - Wilson, William Henry (Reel 52)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 52)
  - Private Collections
    (Inventories and/or transcripts of papers; books; photographs; newspaper articles; talks given (sometimes filed under who owned them, sometimes according to the person who was their subject)
    - Ames, James W. (Dr.) (Reel 52)
    - Barnes, Robert Christopher (Reel 52)
    - Barrat, Alice (Reel 52)
    - Booker T. Washington Trade Association (Reel 52)
    - Burton Historical Collection (Reel 52)
    - Carroll, Leona Gardner (Reel 52)
    - Cayne, Irene Davis (Reel 52)
    - Chandler, Arthur D. (Reel 52)
    - Christian, Thomas H. (Reel 52)
    - Crosby, Carie May (Reel 52)
    - Dancy, John C. (Reel 52)
    - Greene, Mrs. John (Reel 52)
    - Grimes, William H. (Reel 52)
    - Jeffrey, Romaina W. J. (Reel 52)
    - Junior, Hamilton (Reel 52)
    - Lambert, Benjamin Willoughby (Reel 52)
    - League of Catholic Women (Reel 52)
    - Lewis, Ada (Reel 52)
    - Merriweather, William T. (Reel 52)
    - Mumford, Orville (Reel 52)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Youth Council (Reel 52)
    - Negro Nationalist Society of Michigan (Reel 52)
    - Pullman Porters Club (Reel 52)
    - Ridley, Florida R. (Reel 52)
    - St. Matthew's Protestant Episcopal Church (Reel 53)
    - Scott, Bertha J. Stewart (Reel 53)
    - Scott, Minnie Anthony Hicklin (Reel 53)
    - Shewcraft, Richard (Reel 53)
    - Straker, Julius (Reel 53)
    - Turner, A. L. (Dr.) (Reel 53)
    - Urban League, Detroit Branch (Reel 53)
    - Webb, Charles R. (Reel 53)
    - Willing Workers (Reel 53)
    - Wilson, Alfred White (Reel 53)
    - Woods, Julia Watson (Reel 53)
- Transcripts of County Records
  The Transcripts of County Records series consists of transcripts and abstracts of county board of supervisors minutes and of selected village/city council minutes, with the addition, in a few cases, of other types of records as well. Sometimes, there was more than one chronology of what was essentially the same thing, transcribed or abstracted slightly differently by different field workers. Only a portion of the transcribed county records have been microfilmed. A complete listing of all the transcripts, both on microfilm and hard copy, follows the listing of the contents of roll 68
  - Alcona County
    - Proceedings of the Board of Supervisors
      - Vol. 1 July 1869-October 1871, January-February 1876, June 1881-December 1894 (Reel 54)
      - Vol. 2 April 1895-January 1917 (Reel 54)
      - Vol. 3 February 1917-June 1938 (Reel 54)
      - Vol. 4 October 1938-June 1940 (Reel 54)
  - Allegan County 1836-1843 (Box 1)
  - Alpena County 1871-1919, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Alpena County 1871-1919, 1937 (Box 2)
    (continued)
  - Antrim County 1863-1890 (Box 2)
  - Arenac County 1883-1890 (Box 2)
  - Bay County
    - Abstract of Supervisors' Proceedings
      - 1858-1918 (Reel 55)
    - Proceedings of the Board of Supervisors
      - Liber A July 1858-May 1869 (Reel 55)
      - Liber B July 1869-October 1874 (Reel 55)
      - Liber C October 1874-October 1879 (Reel 55)
      - Liber D October 1879-October 1881 (Reel 55)
  - Benzie County 1869-1920
    - Benzonia Township Highway Commissioners Record 1871-1901 (Box 2)
    - Crystal Lake Township Record of Roads 1880-1911 (Box 3)
    - Laws Concerning Keeping of Records (arranged by government department) (Box 3)
  - Berrien County 1832-1941 (Box 3)
  - Berrien County 1832-1941 (Box 4)
  - Berrien County 1832-1941 (Box 5)
  - Calhoun County 1834-1940 (Box 5)
  - Cass County 1831-1867 (Box 5)
  - Charlevoix County 1936 (Box 5)
  - Cheboygan County
    - Motions of Board of Supervisors 1855-1936 (Box 5)
  - Chippewa County
    - 1831-1887, 1937, 1938 (Box 5)
    - St. Marie Township Board Meeting Minutes 1836-1848 (Box 5)
  - Clare County 1871-1925, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Clare County 1871-1925, 1940 (Box 6)
  - Crawford County
    - Abstract of Supervisors' Proceedings (Reel 56)
      - 1879-1902 (Reel 56)
    - Proceedings of the Board of Supervisors
      - Vol. 1 April 1879-January 1887 (Reel 56)
      - Vol. 2 January 1887-October 1887 (Reel 56)
  - Eaton County 1838-1930 (Box 7)
  - Eaton County 1838-1930 (Box 8)
  - Emmet County
    - Abstract of Supervisors' Proceedings
      - October 1857-January 1902 (Reel 56)
      - October 1936-March 1939 (Reel 56)
    - Proceedings of the Board of Supervisors
      - Vol. 1 November 1855-January 1863 (Reel 56)
      - Vol. 2 1863-July 1873 (Reel 56)
      - Vol. 3 October 1874-October 1893 (Reel 57)
      - Vol. 4 October 1894-January 1902 (Reel 57)
      - Vol. 5 June 1902-October 1908 (Reel 57)
      - Vol. 5 June 1902-October 1908 (cont.) (Reel 58)
      - Vol. 6 January 1909-April 1914 (Reel 58)
      - Vol. 6 January 1909-April 1914 (cont.) (Reel 59)
      - Vol. 7 June 1914-November 1918 (Reel 59)
      - Vol. 8 November 1918-October 1921 (Reel 60)
      - Vol. 9 October 1921-June 1925 (Reel 60)
      - Vol. 9 October 1921-June 1925 (cont.) (Reel 61)
      - Vol. 10 October 1925-May 1928 (Reel 61)
      - Vol. 11 October 1928-October 1929 (Reel 62)
  - Genesee County 1836-1895 (Box 8)
  - Genesee County 1836-1895 (Box 9)
  - Gladwin County
    - 1875-1921 (Box 8)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 9)
    - 1940 (Box 10)
  - Gogebic County (Box 10)
    - 1887-1895 (Box 10)
    - Budget 1940-1941 (Box 10)
  - Grand Traverse County 1853-1855 (Box 10)
  - Gratiot County
    - Proceedings of the Board of Supervisors
      - Liber 1 January 1856-January 1858 (Reel 62)
      - Liber 2 October 1858-October 1866 (Reel 62)
      - Liber 3 January 1867-January 1872 (Reel 62)
      - Liber 4 October 1872-June 1879 (Reel 62)
      - Liber 5 October 1879-January 1885 (Reel 63)